Xavier University Rank and Tenure Committee records
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Rank and Tenure Committee records
1956-1989
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). University Rank and Tenure Committee
.8 linear feet (2 boxes)
Meeting agendas and minutes of the Xavier University Rank and Tenure Committee. Included are correspondence files.
XUA-19
History of Xavier University Rank and Tenure Committee
The University Rank and Tenure Committee was first established in the fall of 1945 by the then president, Fr. Celestine Steiner, S.J. It was to concern itself "with the salaries of faculty and staff and professional matters." The committee consisted of Vice President Frederick N. Miller, S.J., and five faculty members (three laymen and two Jesuits)-all appointed by the president. The description of this committee has changed with time.
The Annual Document of University Committees provides the following information on the role, responsibilities, and membership of this committee: "UNIVERSITY RANK AND TENURE COMMITTEE: Charge: The University Rank and Tenure Committee reviews all recommendations and applications for the promotion and tenure of faculty. The committee makes its recommendations to the President regarding promotion and tenure. A fuller description of this committee's responsibilities is in the Faculty Handbook. Membership: Seven (7) tenured, full professors comprise the voting members of the University Rank and Tenure Committee with two members coming from each college, except in the case of the College of Arts and Sciences, which shall be represented by three members, with one or two of these members from the following departments: biology, chemistry, physics, mathematics and computer science. The Academic Vice President/Provost is the chairperson and is a non-voting member. Each year the Principal Faculty elect, in a fixed rotation, one or two full professors to the University Rank and Tenure Committee for a three-year term. These staggered terms provide for election of at least one full professor from each of the three colleges. Each college nominates two tenured, full professors for its opening. The members of the Committee are elected by all of the Principal Faculty. Reporting: The University Rank and Tenure Committee reports through the Academic Vice President/Provost to the President." (Source: Annual Document of University Committees, 2009-2010)
Scope and Content
This collection consists of meeting minutes and agendas, with separate files for committee correspondence.
Statement of Arrangement
Materials are arranged by document type in chronological order: first meeting agendas and minutes and then correspondence.
Restrictions on Access
Restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Faculty; College teachers--Tenure--Ohio
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1958-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)